Fourth-year DPhil Candidate in Computer Science at the **University of Oxford**. Former student researcher at **Google** working on large language model (LLM) evaluation. **Research Fellow** at Stellenbosch University's Unit for the Ethics of Technology.

Rare multi-disciplinary expertise across **STEM** (computer science, requirements engineering), the **humanities** (philosophy, linguistics, practical ethics), the **social sciences** (quantitative & qualitative research, social anthropology), and **interdisciplinary areas** (cognitive science, HCI, responsible innovation, computational linguistics).

Publications

- Alberts, L., Lyngs, U., Van Kleek, M. (2024). "Computers as Bad Social Actors: Dark and Anti-Patterns in Interfaces that Act Socially", *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction, Volume 8, Issue CSCW1*, 202, pp 1–25. DOI
- Gabriel, I., Manzini, A., Keeling, G., Hendricks, L.A., Reiser, V., Iqbal, H., Tomasev, N., Ktena, I., Kenton, Z., Rodriguez, M., El-Sayed, S., ... Manyika, J. 2024. "The Ethics of Advanced AI Assistants". *Google DeepMind*. DOI
- Lize Alberts, Geoff Keeling, Amanda McCroskery (2024). "Should agentic conversational AI change how we think about ethics? Characterising an interactional ethics centred on respect", Under review at AAAI Conference on AI, Ethics, and Society (AIES). arXiv:2401.09082v2. DOI
- Lyngs, U., Lukoff, K., Slovak, P., Inzlicht, M., Freed, M., Andrews, H., Tinsman, C., Csuka, L., Alberts, L., ... Shadbolt, N. (2024). "I finally felt I had the tools to control these urges": Empowering Students to Achieve Their Device Use Goals With the Reduce Digital Distraction Workshop. Proceedings of the CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 251, pp 1-23.DOI
- Alberts, L., Lyngs, U., & Lukoff, K. 2024. "Designing for Sustained Motivation: A Review of Self-Determination Theory in Behaviour Change Technologies", accepted at *Interacting with Computers*. arXiv.2402.00121. DOI
- Lukoff, K., Lyngs, U., & Alberts, L. 2022. "Designing to Support Autonomy and Reduce Psychological Reactance in Digital Self-Control Tools", in Self-Determination Theory in HCI: Shaping a Research Agenda. Workshop at the ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI'22). PDF
- Alberts, L. 2020. "Not Cheating on the Turing Test: Towards Grounded Language Learning in Artificial Intelligence", master's thesis. arXiv.2206.14672. DOI
- Alberts, L. 2019. "Meeting Them Halfway: Altering Language Conventions to Facilitate Human-Robot Interaction". Stellenbosch Papers in Linguistics Plus, 56:97-122. DOI

Work Experience

Student Researcher

July-October 2023

2023-

Google London, UK

I worked for three months as a student researcher in the Cerebra team at Google. I led a project critically evaluating current alignment approaches and frameworks for Large Language Models (LLMs), taxonomised unexplored risks, and proposed a novel ethical framework centred on duties of respect.

Leader of Royal Institution Masterclass in Computer Science

The Royal Institution, UK

I have designed a Royal Institution Masterclass on *Dark Patterns* in user interface design, which I have been leading annually for high school children.

Graduate Research Assistant

2020-2021

Responsible Technology Institute, University of Oxford, UK

I worked as an RA for the EPSRC-funded RoboTIPS project. Using Responsible Innovation (RI) methodology, I assisted with **multi-stakeholder engagement** and constructing **possible scenarios for future technologies**.

Teaching Assistant and Seminar Leader

• University of Oxford, UK

2020-2021

Software Engineering Dept.: Interaction Design, Requirements Engineering Computer Science Dept.: Ethical Computing in Practice, Ethics and Responsible Innovation

• Stellenbosch University, ZA 2018-2019 I helped administer two Philosophy courses and gave seminars thrice a week for groups of 5 to 80 first/third-years.

ullet North-West University, ZA

2015-2017

I was TA for several Philosophy and Art History courses and led weekly seminars.

Education

D.Phil. in Computer Science

Finalising—Passed Confirmation

University of Oxford, UK

My doctorate employs **HCI** methods, as well as critical engagement with **interdisci-plinary** literature, to improve how AI/automated systems treat people in interactions. I particularly focus on **LLM** agents and other systems that behave as social actors. The aims include better supporting user autonomy and wellbeing, as well as anticipating and mitigating risks regarding emerging language technologies.

M.A. (Thesis) in Philosophy

Dec 2020

Stellenbosch University, ZA

Type: Full research thesis (140 pages)

Domains: Philosophy of Mind and Language, Cognitive Science, Cognitive and Computational Linguistics, NLP and NLU (theory)

Title: 'Not cheating on the Turing Test: Towards grounded language learning in AI' Final grade:

Distinction 84%

B.A. (Hons) in Philosophy

Mar 2019

Stellenbosch University, ZA

University of Bristol, UK (4 months Study Abroad)

Bristol: Philosophical Issues of the Physical Sciences, Probability and Rationality Stellenbosch: Nietzsche, Philosophy of Language Average: 80% Dissertation: 'Meeting them halfway: Altering language conventions to facilitate human-robot interaction' (18566 words)

Mark: 88% Final grade:

Cum Laude 82%

B.A. in Humanities

Mar 2018

North-West University (Potchefstroom), ZA

Majors: Philosophy, History of Art, Social Anthropology

Minors: English, History, Communication Studies

Extra modules: 9 (152 extra credits)

Final grade: Distinction 82% (Graduated top of class)

Eldoraigne High School, ZA

Final marks: Information Technology (87%), Maths (83%), Design (97%),

English (85%), Afrikaans (89%), Life Orientation (81%), Dramatic Arts (81%)

Nov 2012 Final grade: **Distinction 87**%

Talks and Panels

- Invited speaker on **Dark Patterns As Hostile Scaffolding** 28 June 2024 Scaffolding Bad Working Group, University of KwaZulu-Natal, UK
- Panellist on Artificial Intelligence versus Natural Stupidity 25 May 2024
 Kellogg College, University of Oxford, UK
- Computers as Bad Social Actors 8 Mar 2024 Princeton ETHICOM AI & Ethics Seminar, Princeton University, NJ, USA
- Dark and Anti-Patterns in Social Interfaces 13 Sep 2023 Google-Cambridge University Reading Group on Conversational Agents, Google London, UK
- Dark and Anti-Patterns in Social Interfaces 10 Sep 2023 TL/UXR, Google, London, UK
- Respect as a Value for Human-Computer Interaction 21 Mar 2022 Institute for Ethics in AI gathering with Accenture, University of Oxford, UK

Research Workshops

Google's Techno-Moral Scenarios for Responsible Innovation 17-19 Oct 2023 Google Research/Responsible Innovation, Google Amsterdam, the Netherlands I was invited to join a select panel of experts from academia and industry to exchange views on using responsible innovation to advance a vision of AI that is empowering, meaningful, and beneficial. We practised using a combination of RI methods (e.g., design fiction, speculative design, and Google's own techno-moral scenario approach) to imaginatively and reflexively engage with ethical concerns regarding new technologies.

Generative AI and Its Impact on Human Creativity 1 Feb 2024 Google and the Graziano Lab, Princeton University, NJ, US I was invited to join a select panel of scholars and Googlers to produce a set of responsi-

ble and ethical recommendations regarding Gen(erative) AI. We reflected on the nature and processes of human creativity, and how GenAI may affect, and ideally support it.

Self-Determination Theory in HCI: Shaping a Research Agenda 9 May 2022 The ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, Hawaii, US I participated in a CHI workshop with other HCI researchers to explore how self-determination theory may aid the design of user-centred technologies.

Skills

- **Programming:** Python (for deep learning, data science); MATLAB (for ML); R; Octave; Object Pascal; C; C#; HTML; JavaScript; SQL; PHP
- GenAI-specific research: Familiarity with RLHF approaches and self-correction strategies for LLMs; experience with prompt engineering, fine-tuning, alignment; creating new benchmarks for LLM evaluation; machine learning/deep learning theory and practice; using responsible innovation methods to evaluate ethical concerns surrounding foundation models.
- Interface Design: Interaction design, requirements engineering, user-centred design, value-sensitive design, speculative design, graphic design
- Empirical research: Quantitative and qualitative social scientific research methods; thematic analysis; systematic and scoping reviews
- Applied research: Cross-disciplinary research; critical and conceptual analysis; applied ethics; evaluating the potential risks/impacts of AI technologies in multidisciplinary teams, multi-stakeholder engagement

• Academic and Creative Writing: Writing/reviewing academic papers, poetry

Additional Certification

• Generative AI with LLMs by deeplearning ai on Coursera

Jun 2024

• Neural Networks and Deep Learning by deeplearning.ai on Coursera Grade: 100% Dec 2018

• Diploma in Web Development by Shaw Academy

Jul 2016

Organisational Experience

Leader of Inter-Departmental Reading Group on LLMs

2023-

The University of Oxford, UK

I lead a biweekly reading group on emerging research on LLMs where Oxford University researchers from Computer Science, Engineering and the Oxford Internet Institute (OII) share their work, discuss new developments in the field, and take GenAI courses.

Co-founder and Organiser of RTI Student Network

2020-

The Responsible Technology Institute (RTI), The University of Oxford, UK The RTI is an international centre of excellence on responsible technology. I co-founded its international student network connecting researchers interested in RI. I help to organise reading groups, expert panel discussions, and work-in-progress seminars.

President of Oxford University CompSoc

2021-2022

The Oxford University Computer Society (CompSoc)

I was the first female president of CompSoc (est. 1978), one of Oxford University's largest and oldest societies for computer science-related interests. I delegated work, engaged with industry sponsors, and helped organise a university-wide hackathon.

Awards and Achievements

Graduate Lighthouse Scholarship

2020

The Responsible Technology Institute and Department of Computer Science, University of Oxford, UK

My doctorate is funded by a highly competitive scholarship awarded by the Responsible Technology Institute.

Awards for Academic Achievement

- Department of Philosophy, North-West University, ZA Mar 2018 Merit certificate for excellent academic achievement in Philosophy (top of class)
- School of Social and Gov. Studies, North-West University, ZA Mar 2016 Merit certificate for best academic achievement in Medical Anthropology
- School of Social and Gov. Studies, North-West University, ZA Mar 2016 Merit certificate for best academic achievement in Urban Anthropology

Member of Golden Key International Honour Society

2016

North-West University (Potchefstroom), ZA

I was invited for being ranked in the top 15% of North-West University's sophomores.